# Vladimir Kostyukov

## **Compiler Engineer**

 $\mathfrak{D}$  +7(923)1319766  $\bowtie$  vladimir.v.kostyukov@gmail.com http://vkostyukov.ru

## **Summary**

Software Engineer with 3 years of experience developing compilers and VMs. Creative and passionate programmer with in-depth knowledges of managed runtimes and compilers. Excellent Java and C/C++ programming skills allied with experience in performance analysis and benchmarking.

#### Skills

Programming Languages Fluent in Java and Scala

Efficient in C/C++

Knowledges in JavaScript, Python, Perl

Scopes

Programming Languages Design and Implementation, Performance Analysis, Object Oriented Programming, Functional Programming, Purely Functional Data Structures, Design and Analysis of Algorithms

## **Experience**

#### 2011/04 - ... Software Engineer, Intel Corporation, Novosibirsk, Russia.

I am a member of the **Managed Runtimes** team. My first project there was development (from scratch) a proof of concept PKCS#11 Java Crypto Provider (5k LOC), which based on Intel IPP libraries. The developed prototype showed 6X speedup relative to the default Java implementation.

I am currently involved into development of the x86 Trace-JIT compiler (targeted to Intel<sup>®</sup> Atom<sup>™</sup> Architecture) for Dalvik VM. More precisely, I am responsible for development of both back-end (including code generation and instruction scheduling) and middle-end (including data-flow analysis and optimizations on CFG) components of the compiler.

Tools: Linux Shell, Git, Gerrit, Bugzilla, GCC, Intel VTune, Intel TBB, Intel IPP

**Keywords:** Performance Analysis, Compilers and Interpreters, JIT Compilation, Low-Level and High-Level Optimizations, Data-Flow Analysis, CFG Construction and Analysis, Instruction Scheduling, Registerization, Benchmarking, Debugging

#### 2010/10 - 2011/04 Software Intern, Intel Corporation, Novosibirsk, Russia.

As a member of **Compilers and Languages** group I was responsible for performance tracking and analysis of Intel Compiler for MIC platform (a GPUGP chip with up to 128 cores). I gained an Intel SSG Award for being a pioneer of Intel MIC compiler performance tracking (developed a Perl-based harness and ported initial four workloads from NVidia CUDA SDK).

Tools: Intel Compiler Collections, Perl, Intel VTune, Linux Shell

**Keywords:** Performance Analysis, GPU Offload, Benchmarking, Multithreading and Concurrency, Synchronization, Parallel Algorithms, Lock-Free Algorithms

#### 2010/07 - 2010/08 Summer School Intern, Intel Corporation, Novosibirsk, Russia.

I was working in **Java Xeon** team on the analysis of bottlenecks in the SPECjvm2008.serial test at Intel's modern architectures. The suggested solution (based on reducing number of stack frames) showed up to 50% speedup on WSM-EX platform (in a multithreaded mode).

Tools: Linux Shell, JDK, GCC, Intel VTune, Vim, SPECjvm2008, Eclipse

**Keywords:** Java Performance Analysis, Benchmarking, Concurrency, JMM, JVM Internals, Serialization

#### 2007/10 - 2010/07

#### Technician, Altai State Technical University, Barnaul, Russia.

While working in IT department, I was responsible for maintaining network environment of university campus. I also was leading a technical support team of ACM ICPC NEERC. **Tools:** *Linux Shell, Clonezilla* 

Keywords: Scripting, OS Cloning, Network Administration

## **Projects**

#### la4j Linear Algebra for Java, http://la4j.org.

The la4j is a lightweight and 100% Java library that provides Linear Algebra primitives and algorithms. It is highly popular sparse/dense matrix library, which combines both fluent API and good performance.

Tools: Java SE, Eclipse, Maven, jUnit, Git, Travis-CI

Keywords: Linear Algebra, Math, API Design, TDD, Design Patterns, Open Source

#### Quipu Programming Language, http://esolangs.org/wiki/Quipu.

The Quipu is an Esoteric programming language inspired by «talking knots» – recording devices historically used by Incas. It is a «believed Turing-complete» language, which means author believes that the language is Turing-complete, but no formal proof was provided.

Tools: Scala

Keywords: Source Code Parsing, Interpretation

## **Education**

#### 2006-2011 Master of Science in CS, Altai State Technical University, Barnaul.

Master's thesis: "Distributed monitoring and dispatching system of the processes in heterogenous environment".

Grade: 95/100

## **Certificates**

- 2010 IPPP-2-12, Intel Parallel Programming Professional.
- 2010 HPC School 2010, Participant Certificate.
- 2010 Intel Summer School 2010, Participant Certificate.
- 2010 Intel Winter School, Participant Certificate.